75. Whales, Silent Tears. We humans think more and more about the effect of our actions
on our environment. We are starting to understand how destroying animal populations can have
far-reaching effects on our planet. We're even starting to consider the rights of animals
as we think about hunting them. However, we rarely discuss how our actions affect animals'
psychological states. Whales are very intelligent and social. They behave in complex, moral
ways. They babysit young whales while their mothers look for food. They can be grateful
for being rescued. One whale, after being freed from a net, didn't swim away but instead
approached and touched every diver who had helped save her. Whales need company to thrive.
They play and interact with many of their species as they travel through the water.
Now, however, there are far fewer animals in many whale species. One French naturalist,
Yves Pagalet, believes that whales are getting lonely. He thinks that the effect hunting
has on whales affects not only their bodies but their minds as well. The small numbers
of whales left behind are confused. They may not understand where the other whales
have gone or why. Pagalet warns that lonely, depressed whales could lose their will to
live. That means that they don't care about living anymore. They may stop eating or do
other unhealthy things. He thinks that when whales get too lonely, they may stop breeding.
It's not only hunting that lowers whale populations. Nets and other dangerous fishing gear, environmental
pollution, and the use of sonar, using sound waves to navigate, are all creating a new,
frightening environment for whales. They may decide that they just don't want to live
in it anymore. Then, unfortunately, whales themselves will finish the job that overhunting
started.